<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Sweat and Neurons</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/maths.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2015-02-04T00:53:52+00:00</updated><entry><title>Life is a 2-D board game!</title><link href="/blog/2015/02/04/life-is-a-2-d-board-game/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-04T00:53:52+00:00</updated><author><name>Siddhant Shrivastava</name></author><id>tag:,2015-02-04:blog/2015/02/04/life-is-a-2-d-board-game/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conway's Game of Life&lt;/strong&gt; or the single-player zero sum game comprised of cellular automata with four simple rules. It reassured me of the beauty of Mathematics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game has intrigued me for quite a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got the opportunity to dabble with the intricate patterns and get to know the rules when I alter the rules. The results are to say the least, quite disastrous. The conditions for Conway's game begin to crumble down with simple changes in the rules. Simulations under way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thinking along the lines of applying the Game of Life in &lt;strong&gt;Pattern Formation problems in Robotics&lt;/strong&gt;. For its automaton-ness...no history, no future. Adaptability to future outcome, modification of rules as and when you like, the tenacity of the patterns. Oscillators, still lifes all can be used in different domains of Robotics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An entire world of Robots can be imagined where all the different kinds of bots follow the rules of the game of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This not only controls the population, but also results in self-sufficient communities. This can teach us things about Android epistemology. For instance, a robot meant for video surveillance would not move, hence lives a  Still Life. A robot meant to patrol a region frequently should be an Oscillator. The simple states of the Automata ensure crispness of pattern formation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However it would be a challenge to deploy robots to the next states in the Automata, ensure which robots to move where, which robots to keep, which robots to summon. Virtually making a cell dead even when a robot lives there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cellular Automata would prove beneficial in self-organizing systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People tried the game with QR codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun Fact: I was introduced to Conway's Game via a strategy board game with the same name - "Game of Life". &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>