<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Sweat and Neurons</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/open-source.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2015-01-10T16:42:14+00:00</updated><entry><title>The LaTeX course of life</title><link href="/blog/2015/01/10/the-latex-course-of-life/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-10T16:42:14+00:00</updated><author><name>Siddhant Shrivastava</name></author><id>tag:,2015-01-10:blog/2015/01/10/the-latex-course-of-life/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer internships' deadlines knell by as I key this post. A common section in all application forms is the Curriculum Vitae/Résumé. Having made 2 versions of my résumé in Microsoft Word, the FOSS enthusiast in me felt the pinch. I decided- my résumé should be in LaTeX - the typesetting framework based on Knuth's TeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having just a theoretical knowledge of how LaTeX worked, I probed into the open-source community. Forked Debarghya Das' résumé which I liked because of its brevity and summarization in just one page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This exercise taught me the importance of documentation, yet again. I was not merely modifying someone's LaTeX code. The documentation was edifying and I actually learnt a lot in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, enough said. I urge you to try out LaTeX if you haven't already. It has a steep learning curve for certain - but I am sure the hacker in you will be happy to help you climb the TeXy mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, back to completing my application forms :) &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="computers"></category><category term="foss"></category><category term="open source"></category><category term="typesetting"></category><category term="professional"></category></entry><entry><title>Lessons from the Octopress Setup</title><link href="/blog/2014/06/11/lessons-from-the-octopress-setup/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-11T23:37:37+00:00</updated><author><name>Siddhant Shrivastava</name></author><id>tag:,2014-06-11:blog/2014/06/11/lessons-from-the-octopress-setup/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post on this blog. I am learning to play with the various commands and get a knack of the basic publishing workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;This is how syntax highlighting is done
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After creating &lt;code&gt;.markdown&lt;/code&gt; files, all one has to do is to push changes to the master branch of the remote repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;bundle exec rake generate
bundle exec rake deploy
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Git commands to be used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To update the &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; branch with the latest changes (it is recommended to keep a backup)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git add .
git commit -m &amp;quot;source update #&amp;quot;
git push origin source
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;whereas to revert to the master branch, go to the _deploy directory, and run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git pull origin master
bundle exec rake deploy
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To-do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add pages: about, travel, competitive programming, open source contributions, BITS work, SciTech News, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the different plugins that are available for the blog, and use some of them - like Google Analytics, g+ integration, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, after posting couple of posts on Blogger and WordPress, I feel at home@Octopress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="computers"></category><category term="foss"></category><category term="linux"></category></entry></feed>