<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>All Day I Dream About Science</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-06-16T22:43:56+00:00</updated><entry><title>The Tree of Life</title><link href="/blog/2014/06/16/the-tree-of-life/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-16T22:43:56+00:00</updated><author><name>Siddhant Shrivastava</name></author><id>tag:,2014-06-16:blog/2014/06/16/the-tree-of-life/</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching Cosmos [S01E02]. Neil deGrasse Tyson speaks about artificial and natural selection ( dog breeds, and polar bears; respectively ). He also talks that we share our DNA with plants, and furthermore, plants and humans share DNA with birds, etc..So we can backtrack in a similar inductive fashion to reason that life started as ONE COMMON ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I think?
We have ML, and DM backtracking mechanisms available. Why not think in this direction, that we can establish a correlation between different species, a coming together of various kingdoms, in a way that both explains and justifies evolution - both in the artificial, and the natural way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hunches are sometimes right, and mostly overstated. But we can try, right? It'll teach us a lot of things. Firstly it'll make us better at looking at ourselves, at the world as one great family (that's what Vasudev Kutumb is all about, right?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can use backtracking to predict disease vectors, and weather conditions (from the IIRS orientation session), I believe we can collectively develop a genealogy project for species all over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, why am I learning all the tools to process data, and to code? To make the world a better place, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, we don't need to save the planet, the planet is strong enough to sustain itself; we need to save ourselves, from the disasters we can cause artificially.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="astronomy"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="learning"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="universe"></category></entry></feed>